<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Duy Do - Thougths on computer</title>
    <link>http://duydo.me/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Duy Do - Thougths on computer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Duy Do</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 09:33:30 +0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://duydo.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tầm quan trọng của việc đọc sách</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/tam-quan-trong-cua-viec-doc-sach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2018 09:33:30 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/tam-quan-trong-cua-viec-doc-sach/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lâu nay muốn viết về tầm quan trọng của việc đọc sách để chia sẻ với mấy đứa cháu ở nhà cũng như để nhắc nhở bản thân mà lười quá chưa viết, hôm qua tình cờ đọc được &lt;a href=&#34;http://science-technology.vn/?p=5565&#34;&gt;bài viết của giáo sư John Vu&lt;/a&gt; về chủ đề này, thấy khá phù hợp với suy nghĩ của mình nên mình chia sẻ lại ở đây.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ngày nay học sinh không đọc sách mà ưa thích các thiết bị điện tử.  Ngay cả trong lớp của tôi, nhiều học sinh đều đặn nhìn vào điện thoại di  động và laptop của họ để xem tin nhắn ngắn từ bạn bè hay tin tức từ  Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Năm ngoái các khảo cứu của chính phủ Mĩ thấy rằng từ năm 1990, số  phần trăm học sinh trung học là người đọc sách đã giảm từ 75% xuống 52%,  và số phần trăm sinh viên đại học đã giảm từ 64% xuống 32%.  Nhưng số  phần trăm này che giấu một điều quan trọng: Phần lớn điều họ đọc là từ  Google, Twitter, tin nhắn và Facebook, không phải văn học, lịch sử, hay  thậm chí tiểu thuyết. Ngay cả một số người lớn cũng dừng đọc sách và báo  chí. Điều họ đọc phần lớn là cái gì đó ngắn, dễ đọc và dễ quên thay vì cái gì đó có nghĩa. Một giáo sư than:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dường như chúng ta đang đi tới  một thế hệ &amp;ldquo;không hiểu biết mới&amp;rdquo;. Những người này chỉ đọc lướt qua cái  gì đó để cho họ có thể nói theo kiểu hội thoại hàng ngày nhưng không  hiểu sâu về bất kì chủ đề nào họ đang nói tới.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Một nhà tâm lí có lần đã nói với tôi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vấn đề là trẻ em không đọc  sách vì bố mẹ chúng không đọc nữa. Anh nhìn vào mọi gia đình ngày nay và  hỏi bao nhiêu bố mẹ đang đọc cùng con họ? Bao nhiêu người trong số họ  đang đọc vì thích thú? Hay họ ưa thích TV, Netflix hay YouTube. Trẻ em  lớn lên khi nhìn bố mẹ chúng, và bố mẹ vẫn hỏi tại sao con họ không đọc  sách? Tại sao tri thức của chúng nông cạn thế? Tại sao chúng không nghĩ  sâu sắc hơn? Tại sao chúng không có đủ kiên nhẫn? Tại sao chúng phát cáu  dễ dàng? Câu trả lời là đơn giản: Vì não chúng đang phát triển với tốc  độ của Internet và xung điện tử.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trẻ em sẽ đọc nếu bố mẹ chúng đọc. Chúng sẽ đọc nhiều hơn vì bố mẹ  chúng làm gương về hành vi đọc tốt. Nếu bố mẹ bao giờ cũng đọc sách cùng  chúng khi chúng còn nhỏ, chúng sẽ phát triển thói quen đọc tốt khi  chúng lớn lên. Khi tôi du hành ở Nhật Bản, tôi thấy mọi người ở đó đọc  nhiều, gần như ở mọi nơi, trong ga tầu hoả, hay trong đường ngầm, và  trong nhà hàng. Bạn tôi giải thích, nhiều gia đình Nhật Bản có qui tắc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Đọc sách đầu tiên, trước khi xem chương trình ti vi hay trò chơi  video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yêu cầu đọc là quãng một giờ mỗi ngày cho trẻ em trường tiểu học  hay một cuốn sách một tuần cho học sinh trung học. Với người Nhật Bản, là người lớn nghĩa là cảm thấy thoải mái với sách. Có lí trí nghĩa là đã  đọc nhiều sách. Trong cuộc hội thoại điển hình, mọi người thường trích  dẫn các cụm từ từ những tiểu thuyết nổi tiếng, biến cố lịch sử, hay thậm  chí sách triết học v.v. Chúng tôi khuyến khích đọc bằng việc để nhiều  sách ở nhà và đặt thời gian hàng ngày cho con cái đọc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Một khảo cứu khác ở Đức cũng chỉ ra rằng có tương quan lớn giữa hành  động và sự thường xuyên của bố mẹ với điều con cái đọc. Trong số các trẻ  em là những người đọc thường xuyên, trên 72% bố mẹ chúng đã đặt thời  gian mỗi ngày để đọc cùng chúng. Nhưng khảo cứu này đi xa hơn để đặt  tương ứng giữa những học sinh đọc nhiều và thành công của họ trong  trường. Kết quả là rõ ràng, 86% trẻ em là người đọc thường xuyên đã vào  đại học khi so với 34% trẻ em không phải là người đọc thường xuyên.  Nhưng khảo cứu này cũng thấy rằng hành vi đọc tốt không liên quan gì tới  công nghệ. Máy đọc điện tử e-readers, máy tính bảng, laptop tất cả đều  có khả năng chuyển giao tài liệu đọc tốt. Sách không chỉ là giấy mà có  thể được đọc từ thiết bị điện tử nữa. Cho nên vấn đề không phải là liệu  thiết bị điện tử có là nguy hiểm cho việc đọc không, mà nội dung của tài  liệu đọc và thói quen đọc mới là cần thiết.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Một giáo sư tâm lí học có lần đã nói với tôi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Với mọi bằng chứng rõ  ràng, điều bản chất với bố mẹ là đọc cho con cái họ khi chúng còn nhỏ vì  đó là sự phát triển phần não mấu chốt của chúng và giáo dục tương lai  của chúng. Anh không thể &amp;ldquo;khoán ngoài&amp;rdquo; giáo dục con anh cho người khác  rồi phàn nàn rằng họ không giúp cho chúng. Giáo dục yêu cầu bố mẹ tham  gia từ sớm, đặc biệt trong tuổi mấu chốt nhất từ bốn tới mười hai tuổi  khi não chúng đang phát triển, và họ cần chắc con cái họ đọc sách.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cách trẻ em đọc và điều chúng đọc sẽ xác định nhiều về thái độ của  người lớn về thế giới bao quanh họ. Trong thời đại thông tin nơi mọi thứ  đang xảy ra nhanh chóng, bạn cần có gốc rễ vững chắc hay tri thức sâu  để duy trì viễn cảnh nhìn cuộc sống của bạn; bằng không bạn sẽ bị ảnh  hưởng bởi nhiều thứ tới mức điều đó có thể đẩy bạn ra khỏi việc kiểm  soát.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview at Elastic</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/interview-at-elastic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2017 09:48:56 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/interview-at-elastic/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some months ago, I had an interview with &lt;a href=&#34;https://elastic.co&#34;&gt;Elastic&lt;/a&gt; for Java Software/Support Engineer position. The interview was an interesting experience I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had, Elastic is a brilliant company with great people and amazing culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interview process is extremely thorough, all conversations were over the video call. It took two months, ten interviews with different engineers, two VPs of Engineers, and the last one is co-founder, Shay Banon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first conversation I had with the technical recruiter, she is very prompt and friendly. She tried to understand my background, my interests, my familiar with Elasticsearch and its ecosytems. The next five conversations I had with five engineers, they are extremely knowledgeable and enjoyable. The last three conversations with VPs and Shay were extremely interesting. We talked about development philosophies, the product vision, the culture, the people at Elastic and the country where you come from; Shay is excited to know many interesting things about your country. They care deeply about building a world class team and delivering outstanding products. I was very impressed the way they organize a distributed team with more than 300 employees in over 30 countries around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technical questions were not too difficult, I believe that you can answer most of those questions if you have solid background about software engineering, distributed systems and of course, about Elasticsearch stack. You don&amp;rsquo;t need to master all Elastic&amp;rsquo;s products to work as a support engineer, the people in your team will help you with the products you are not familliar with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My interview was very smooth, I went in the final round with Shay, and got very positive feedback from him. I was holding in my hand a wonderful oppurtunity to work with the talented people at Elastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In meantime, there was an event happened to me. An investor from US came to me and asked me to do a startup with my friends to build an online platform, this was also a wonderful oppurtunity, wasn&amp;rsquo;t it? This made me think a lot, I had to make a choice: Elastic or my own business. After carefull consideration, I chose to do my own business. I know a startup is not going to be easy and has a bundle of risks but it will be fun. Honestly, that was a tough decision I&amp;rsquo;ve ever made. I really love Elasticsearch and had a dream that one day I could work with Shay and his amazing team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I don&amp;rsquo;t work for Elastic, I will still continue to contribute to Elasticsearch. The Elasticsearch community is amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I want to send my big thanks to Mark Walkom, who referred me to Elastic team :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EVM - Elasticsearch Version Manager</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/evm-elasticsearch-version-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 May 2017 17:50:35 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/evm-elasticsearch-version-manager/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As an Elasticsearch consultant, I often work with different versions of Elasticsearch. To make my developer life easier, I created &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/duydo/evm&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;evm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It allows me to install, remove, test multiple versions easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;installation&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just download the &lt;code&gt;evm&lt;/code&gt; script and make it executable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;sudo curl -o /usr/local/bin/evm https://raw.githubusercontent.com/duydo/evm/master/evm
sudo chmod +x /usr/local/bin/evm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;usage&#34;&gt;Usage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 4
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 5
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 6
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 7
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 8
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt; 9
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;10
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;11
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;12
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;13
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;evm -h                                     Print &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;help&lt;/span&gt; information
evm -V                                     Print version information
evm list                                   List all installed ES versions
evm version                                Print the current activated ES version
evm install &amp;lt;version&amp;gt;                      Install a specific ES version
evm use &amp;lt;version&amp;gt;                          Use a specific ES version
evm remove &amp;lt;version&amp;gt;                       Remove a specific ES version &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; available
evm which &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;version&amp;gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;                      Print path to installed ES version
evm plugin list                            List all installed ES plugins
evm plugin &amp;lt;install&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;remove&amp;gt; &amp;lt;plugin&amp;gt;       Install or remove an ES plugin
evm start &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;-c &amp;lt;/path/to/config/dir&amp;gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;       Start ES in the background with a specific config directory &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;optional&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
evm stop                                   Stop ES &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; it is running
evm status                                 Check &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; ES is running&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;example&#34;&gt;Example&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;4
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;5
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;6
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;7
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;8
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;evm install &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;.3.1                          Install ES &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;.3.1
evm use &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;.3.1                              Use ES &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;.3.1
evm start                                  Start ES node with the default config directory
evm start -c /etc/elasticsearch            Start ES node with /etc/elasticsearch config directory
evm status                                 Print ES running status
evm stop                                   Stop ES &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; it is running
evm plugin install x-pack                  Install the x-pack plugin
evm plugin remove x-pack                   Remove the x-pack plugin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to build Elasticsearch Vietnamese Analysis Plugin</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/how-to-build-elasticsearch-vietnamese-analysis-plugin/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/how-to-build-elasticsearch-vietnamese-analysis-plugin/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve received many requests to build the Vietnamese Analysis plugin when a new version of Elasticsearch is released but sometimes I&amp;rsquo;m not available to do it immediately. In case of urgent, you can build the plugin yourself with following steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-1-install-java-maven-git&#34;&gt;Step 1: Install Java, Maven &amp;amp; Git&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plugin is written in Java and built with Maven, so you have to install them first. Here is the instructions for installing  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.java.com/en/download/help/download_options.xml&#34;&gt;Java&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://maven.apache.org/install.html&#34;&gt;Maven&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/install-git&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using Mac, just use these commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;brew cask install java
brew install maven
brew install git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-2-build-the-vntokenizer&#34;&gt;Step 2: Build the VnTokenizer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plugin is based on the VNTokenizer library, you have to build it before building the plugin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;git clone https://github.com/duydo/vn-nlp-libraries.git
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; vn-nlp-libraries/nlp-parent
mvn install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-3-build-the-plugin&#34;&gt;Step 3: Build the plugin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clone the plugin&amp;rsquo;s source code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;git clone https://github.com/duydo/elasticsearch-analysis-vietnamese.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit the &lt;code&gt;elasticsearch-analysis-vietnamese/pom.xml&lt;/code&gt; to change the version of Elasticsearch you want to build the plugin with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-xml&#34; data-lang=&#34;xml&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;3
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;4
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;5
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;6
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;7
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-xml&#34; data-lang=&#34;xml&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;properties&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  ...
    &lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;project.build.java.version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;1.8&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;/project.build.java.version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;elasticsearch.version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;5.2.1&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;/elasticsearch.version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;lucene.version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;6.4.1&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;/lucene.version&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    ...
&lt;span class=&#34;nt&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;/properties&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Build the plugin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; elasticsearch-analysis-vietnamese
mvn package&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-4-install-the-plugin&#34;&gt;Step 4: Install the plugin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;
&lt;table class=&#34;lntable&#34;&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;lnt&#34;&gt;2
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;lntd&#34;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;mvn clean package
bin/elasticsearch-plugin install file:target/releases/elasticsearch-analysis-vietnamese-5.2.1.zip&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solve your search and analytics problems with Elasticsearch</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/solve-your-search-and-analytics-problems-with-elasticsearch/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 08:07:09 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/solve-your-search-and-analytics-problems-with-elasticsearch/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This slide was for my talk about Elasticsearch at Barcamp Saigon 2016. We&amp;rsquo;ve discussed how to apply Elasticsearch to solve search and analytics problems, how Elasticsearch has been used at GitHub, Uber and Sentifi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;talk_frame_370710&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/player/9fa7022cc8da4e06be30f5e84ab03248&#34; width=&#34;710&#34; height=&#34;399&#34; style=&#34;border:0; padding:0; margin:0; background:transparent;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Elasticsearch cluster works</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/how-elasticsearch-cluster-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 11:16:00 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/how-elasticsearch-cluster-works/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series covering the architecture of Elasticsearch based on my experience while working with it. In this post, we’ll be discussing how the cluster works, try to find answers for following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How a node in cluster talks to others?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens when a node joins or leaves the cluster?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens when a node stops or has encountered a problem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-cluster-of-nodes&#34;&gt;A Cluster of Nodes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we start an instance of Elasticsearch, we are starting a &lt;em&gt;node&lt;/em&gt; and we have a &lt;em&gt;cluster&lt;/em&gt; with single node. We start another instance of Elasticsearch has same &lt;code&gt;cluster.name&lt;/code&gt; with the first instance and we have a cluster with two nodes. We can start more instances of Elasticsearch to form a cluster with number of nodes we want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every node in the cluster knows about the other nodes within the cluster, they talk to others directly using the native Elasticsearch language over &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transmission_Control_Protocol&#34;&gt;TCP&lt;/a&gt;. This is known as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_topology#Mesh&#34;&gt;full connected mesh topology&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/3c/NetworkTopology-FullyConnected.png&#34; alt=&#34;full connected mesh topology&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure 1. Full connected mesh topology (source &lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/3c/NetworkTopology-FullyConnected.png&#34;&gt;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/3c/NetworkTopology-FullyConnected.png&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides that, the nodes are able to talk to external world using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.json.org&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ldquo;language&amp;rdquo; over &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext_Transfer_Protocol&#34;&gt;HTTP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we can say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elasticsearch is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer&#34;&gt;peer-to-peer&lt;/a&gt; based system, nodes communicate with others directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each node in the cluster plays one or more roles; it can be a &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; node, &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; node, &lt;em&gt;client&lt;/em&gt; node, or &lt;em&gt;tribe&lt;/em&gt; node. Ech role has it own purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The master node&lt;/strong&gt; is responsible for creating, deleting indices, adding the nodes or remove the nodes from the cluster. Each time a cluster state is changed, the master node broadcasts the changes to other nodes in the cluster. There is only one master node in the cluster at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The data node&lt;/strong&gt; is responsible for holding the data in the shards and performing data related operations such as create, read, update, delete, search, and aggregations. We can have many data nodes in the cluster. If one of the data nodes stops, the cluster still operates and  re-organizes the data on other nodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The client node&lt;/strong&gt; is responsible for routing the cluster-related requests to the master node and the data-related requests to the data nodes, it acts as a &amp;ldquo;smart &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Router_(computing)&#34;&gt;router&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;. The client node does not hold any data, it also cannot become the master node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://duydo.me/images/es_client_to_data_nodes.png&#34; alt=&#34;es_client_to_data_nodes&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 2. The client node routes the data-related request to every data nodes in the cluster.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://duydo.me/images/es_client_to_master_node.png&#34; alt=&#34;es_client_to_data_nodes&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Figure 3. The client node routes the cluster-related request to the master node in the cluster.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The tribe node&lt;/strong&gt; is special type of client node that is able to talk to multiple clusters to perform search and other operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ingest node&lt;/strong&gt; is responsible for pre-processing documents before the actual indexing takes into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we know role of each node, next we look at what happens behind the sence when a node joins or leaves the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;add-a-node-to-the-cluster&#34;&gt;Add a Node to the Cluster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we start a node, the node is starting to ping all the nodes in the cluster for finding the master node. Once the master  is found, it will ask the master  to join by sending a join request; the master accepts it as a new node of the cluster and then notify all the nodes in the cluster about presense of the new node, and finally the new node connects to all other nodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the joined node is a data node, the master will reallocate the data evenly across the nodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remove-a-node-from-the-cluster&#34;&gt;Remove a Node from the Cluster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we stop a node or a node in the cluster is unresponsive in specific amout of time, the master node will remove it from the cluster and reallocate the data if the removed node is a data node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be curious about how the master node knows if other nodes in the cluster are still alive. The master has a fault detection machanism, it pings all the other nodes in the cluster and verify that they are alive or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And about the master, what happens if it stops or has encountered a problem? Same the master node, each node in the cluster also have a fault detection machanism, it pings to master to verify if its still alive. If the master is not alive, other master-eligible nodes will be elected new master to replace the down one within seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next post in this series, we will look at how Elasticsearc index data in a distributed maner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 16:54:21 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/about/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Duy Do is a passionate software engineer with strong background in computer science and mathematics. His areas of interest include distributed systems, search engine, data processing, data analytics, machine learning and performance optimizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is a co-founder of KromLab, an influencer marketing company, where he and his team build the leading marketplace for influencers, connecting right brands with the right creators, enabling branded content that reaches the right audience and inspires action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He loves open sources, he loves community building. You can find his open source softwares on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/duydo&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; or join &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/groups/elasticsearchvn/&#34;&gt;Elasticsearch community for Vietnamese&lt;/a&gt;, where he found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also find him somewhere else on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/duydo&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or the roads he runs every morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He looks like this.&lt;/p&gt;











&lt;span class=&#34;caption-wrapper&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&#34;caption&#34; src=&#34;http://duydo.me/images/duydo_at_half_marathon.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Duy Do conquered his first trail half-marathon at Dalat Ultra Trail 2019.&#34; alt=&#34;Duy Do conquered his first trail half-marathon at Dalat Ultra Trail 2019.&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;caption-text&#34;&gt;Duy Do conquered his first trail half-marathon at Dalat Ultra Trail 2019.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elasticsearch for Data Engineers</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/elasticsearch-for-data-engineers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 18:26:39 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/elasticsearch-for-data-engineers/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the slide for my talk about Elasticsearch for Data Engineers at &lt;a href=&#34;https://sentifi.com&#34;&gt;Sentifi&lt;/a&gt;, it was only for beginners who are not familiar with Elasticsearch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;talk_frame_359449&#34; src=&#34;//speakerdeck.com/player/970178bcd293418cb303b342fa7d77f5&#34; width=&#34;710&#34; height=&#34;399&#34; style=&#34;border:0; padding:0; margin:0; background:transparent;&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celery - a Distributed Task Queue</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/celery-a-distributed-task-queue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 08:28:45 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/celery-a-distributed-task-queue/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My talk about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.celeryproject.org&#34;&gt;Celery&lt;/a&gt; when I was working at &lt;a href=&#34;http://sentifi.com&#34;&gt;Sentifi&lt;/a&gt;.
Celery is an asynchronous task queue/job queue based on distributed message passing.    It is focused on real-time operation, but supports scheduling as well.
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe
  style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 500px;&#34;
  frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
  marginwidth=&#34;0&#34;
  marginheight=&#34;0&#34;
  scrolling=&#34;no&#34;
  src=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/50704487?rel=0&#34;
    allowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;
    webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;
    mozallowfullscreen=&#34;true&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nhà Giả Kim - Paulo Coelho</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/nh%C3%A0-gi%E1%BA%A3-kim-paulo-coelho/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2016 17:59:15 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/nh%C3%A0-gi%E1%BA%A3-kim-paulo-coelho/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nhà Giả Kim&amp;rdquo; là câu chuyện về chàng chăn cừu Santiago ở tận xứ Tây Ban Nha, đã từ bỏ những kế hoạch vạch sẵn của ba mẹ cho mình để chọn lấy cuộc sống &amp;ldquo;nay đây mai đó&amp;rdquo;, để theo đuổi ước mơ vận mệnh của mình.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sách dường như là vật bất li thân của chàng, mỗi lúc chăn cừu chàng luôn có một cuốn sách bên cạnh. Điều này làm mình nhớ đến tuổi thơ của mình, lúc nào đi chăn bò cũng mang theo một cuốn sách ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Câu chuyện nhẹ nhàng, tinh tế, hơi thần bí nhưng chứa đựng những thông điệp vô cùng ý nghĩa từ các nhân vật trong truyện. Mình thấy không có nhân vật nào thừa trong câu chuyện, từ những vĩ nhân thông thái như nhà vua xứ Salem, nhà giả kim đến những con người bình thường như anh bán kem, ông chủ cửa hàng pha lê, anh chàng người Anh, cô gái sa mạc, người phu lạc đà và cả những tên cướp trong sa mạc Sahara.  Dẫu đến từ những vùng đất khác nhau,  dẫu có nhiều điểm khác biệt nhưng các nhân vật đều có một điểm chung: họ có ước mơ, có vận mệnh của đời mình nhưng không phải ai cũng đi theo nó đến cùng, không phải ai cũng đưa ra được lựa chọn giữa &amp;ldquo;một bên là những gì quen thuộc gần gũi và một bên là những gì mình muốn sở hữu&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hành trình đi tìm kho báu của chàng chăn cừu Santiago đầy gian nan và thử thách, có những lúc tưởng chừng như chàng gục ngã, tưởng chừng như chàng bỏ cuộc thậm chí là bỏ mạng nhưng nhờ niềm tin mãnh liệt vào những dấu hiệu mà con tim lý trí mách bảo, với lòng dũng cảm, sự chân thành và lòng quyết tâm theo đuổi ước mơ, vận mệnh, cuối cùng chàng đã tìm được kho báu của đời mình.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chàng đã đạt được ước  mơ của đời mình nhưng thật sự những thứ quý giá nhất đối với cuộc đời là những gì chàng học được, cảm được trong suốt hành trình ấy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Câu chuyện kết thúc tốt đẹp, mở toan ra những cánh cửa cho những con người có hoài bão, ước mơ, quyết tâm theo đuổi đến cùng vận mệnh của mình.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kho báu không phải là đích đến, kho báu là cả cuộc hành trình&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
