<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Duy Do</title>
    <link>http://duydo.me/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Duy Do</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Duy Do</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 12:10:30 +0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://duydo.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 12:10:30 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/post/</guid>
      
        <description></description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 16:54:21 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/about/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Duy Do is a software engineer with strong background in both computer science and mathematics. His areas of interest include distributed systems, search engine, data processing, data analytics, machine learning and performance optimizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is a co-founder of KromLab, an influencer marketing company, where he and his partners build the leading marketplace for influencers, connecting right brands with the right creators, enabling branded content that reaches the right audience and inspires action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He loves open sources, he loves community building. You can find his open source softwares on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/duydo&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; or join &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/groups/elasticsearchvn/&#34;&gt;Elasticsearch community for Vietnamese&lt;/a&gt;, where he found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also find him somewhere else on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/duydo&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; or the roads he runs every morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He looks like this.&lt;/p&gt;










&lt;p class=&#34;caption-wrapper&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&#34;caption&#34; src=&#34;http://duydo.me/images/duydo_at_half_marathon.jpg&#34; title=&#34;Duy Do conquered his first trail half-marathon at Dalat Ultra Trail 2019.&#34; alt=&#34;Duy Do conquered his first trail half-marathon at Dalat Ultra Trail 2019.&#34;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&#34;caption-text&#34;&gt;Duy Do conquered his first trail half-marathon at Dalat Ultra Trail 2019.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elasticsearch Consulting</title>
      <link>http://duydo.me/consulting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://duydo.me/consulting/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With nearly a decade of professional experience working with Elasticsearh and deep understanding of how it works internally, I&amp;rsquo;ve helped many customers successfully with Elasticsearch-based solutions. I offer followings consulting services:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Architect search applications based on your specific use case, data volume, growth needs and business requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimize queries, index mapping and tune relevancy for existing Elasticsearch implementations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tune, scale Elasticsearch clusters to meet your needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Migrate legacy search engines to Elasticsearch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop Elasticsearch plugins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-customers-are-saying&#34;&gt;What Customers Are Saying&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dang Phan&lt;/strong&gt;, Product Manager at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.go1.com/&#34;&gt;GO1.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duy helped solve our problem. As our product is growing, we need a new scalable and high performance search service for our complex data structure. Duy helped to architect our Elasticsearch service in the best way, which has resulted in a much better service for our clients. Everyone was happy with the end result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Atul Signh&lt;/strong&gt;, Founder &amp;amp; CEO at &lt;a href=&#34;https://theshelf.com&#34;&gt;TheShelf.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duy is a perfect professional! He understands the inner workings of Elasticsearch system and was able to figure out our codebase and then make changes to it so that the performance was improved very quickly! He delivers on time and is always available and he always provides options for us to further improve the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nick Herford&lt;/strong&gt;, Founder at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ultimatelysocial.com/&#34;&gt;Ultimately Social&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outstanding performance by Duy. He&amp;rsquo;s the master of Elasticsearch. What&amp;rsquo;s more, he was very responsive, polite, professional and has perfect command of the English language. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t hesitate one second to hire him again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;need-my-help&#34;&gt;Need my help?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Get in touch](mailto:doquocduy@gmail.com?subject=Elasticsearch Consulting) and work with me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
